Brain organoid biohybrid computers
continue to outpace AI when it comes to
embodied tasks and researchers have
begun giving them various sensations in
a virtual world. Yes, brain organoids,
the tiny human brains that you can grow
in a literal jar if you want to from
human stem cells. They can do a lot of
stuff including forms of computation. We
have come a long way since 2022. It's
only been 4 years since researchers
first claimed sentience in the brain
organoids.
Now, this paper did cause quite a stir
in the neuroscience community. Brain
organoids can learn using dopamine or
ordered or disordered signals. They
think that order is pleasurable and
disorder is uncomfortable. This along
with their capacity to learn in a
biological sense led to researchers
claiming sentience. But seeing as
sentience is not really a well-defined
thing and it's nearly impossible to
prove that you have the capacity to have
an experience, that was debated and
people thought that they were overly
anthropomorphizing brain organoids. But
I actually would agree that if they're
capable of preference, you could
consider that sentience. But if we
really require something living to
understand the experience it's having,
we may disclude things like fish or
insects and it gets a little weird when
we're talking about lab-made artificial
organisms.
Nonetheless, let's talk embodiment.
Researchers recently found that brain
organoids could engage in goal-directed
behavior. So when we're talking about
agency from an
LLM, when a brain organoid decides to do
something it's because it has a
physiological need. Many researchers
also argue that in order to have true
intelligence, you have to have a
physiological need that you need to
maintain. If you're just doing stuff
because you're doing it, it's different
than if you're doing it in order to
maintain some internal homeostasis. The
reason that biological organisms do
anything is to meet our needs when it
comes to breathing or interacting with
others because you have social needs or
going to the fridge to get cheese at
2:00 a.m. It's all about maintaining our
bodies. But let's talk about embodying
brain organoids and giving them
sensation. You can grow a brain
organoid, that's easy. You can even keep
them alive for 5 years or more, but you
also have to interact with them.
Interaction is highly necessary for
proper development. If you do nothing
with them and just let them sit
indefinitely, yeah, they will tend to
degrade. They are, after all, made of
neurons, and neurons do really like to
have something to do. They embody them
using a closed-loop learning system. So,
the brain organoids would have just
random neural activity. That neural
activity would be recorded, decoded, and
then information would be given back to
them about what they're doing in the
virtual world. Now, I know this is a
pretty simple diagram, but this is
actually pretty incredible. They have an
odor field, so they drop the brain
organoids in game world, and they have
to go and find their food reward. When
they find it, they get ordered signals,
which brain organoids seem to enjoy
rather than disorder. You can also train
them on dopamine, but that wasn't
utilized here.
But they also outcompeted AI at the same
task. This is exactly what they found
when they dropped them in game world and
had them play Pong for the first time.
This happened in 2022, and they were
outperforming AI then. Both AI and brain
organoids are getting better, and brain
organoids continue to excel at tasks
that humans would do. Now, much like our
brains, there's some things that
organoids are just not as good at, like
doing simple calculations. Yes, you can
get them to do it, but AI outpaces them
there.
But much like us, what they're really
good at is embodied tasks, things like
navigation or controlling a squishy
robot, as well as things like language
recognition. And unlike AI, using them
as agency is biological agency in
pursuit of a goal that is physiological.
And multiple research groups and
multiple publications have found that
yes, brain organoids will pursue a goal
for a reward. If you really want is an
artificial intelligence system that has
agency that is most similar to us making
biohybrid AI maybe the way to go.
Building biohybrid computers is not just
for fun, although it is kind of fun.
There's a lot of benefits including the
fact that they use far less power than
our traditional computer models. I mean,
hey, open AI is planning to build a data
center that uses the same amount of
power as all of India. Our brain operate
on 20 watts, which is not even a
particularly bright light bulb. Some
researchers also think that this is how
we get the human level models. This is
how we can get to intelligence that is
comparable to our own. Although, if we
are being perfectly honest here, I'm not
sure our own intelligence should really
be the goal. I would think we should go
further than that. In terms of actually
making brain organoids useful on a mass
scale, yeah, we are getting closer.
There is of course the L1 clone for
short, and that is a personal computer,
but servers do exist and researchers are
scaling up. And this could probably be a
video all on its own because a brain
organoid can live and learn, but it
eventually expires. I mean, some of them
expire after about 3 months and that is
the case with CL1, and some of them can
live for many years, but we haven't made
that long life useful. They still need
to be able to teach the next generation
what they've learned during their
lifetimes, and that's something that
researchers are working on. The concept
of a knowledge transplant just feels
wrong.
I will continue to bring you guys the
bleeding edge of brain organoid research
in part because I just really enjoy
talking about it. I hope you've enjoyed
this. Follow for more.